Alvah A. Torrance papers, Inclusive: 1938-1972, undated, Bulk: 1949-1965
Baylor University, The Texas Collection
Alvah A. Torrance papers
Inclusive: 1938-1972, undated, Bulk: 1949-1965
Baylor University, The Texas Collection http://www.baylor.edu/lib/texas/
3085
Torrance, Alvah A.
1 document box 1 OVZ folder 1 OVZ box
The Alvah Allen Torrance papers highlight his work with the Amicable Life Insurance Company and its merger with American Life Insurance Company. Travel notebooks, correspondence, photographs, and several publications are included. Also included are slides of his work as an amateur photographer.
Administrative Information
Physical Description
General condition: Good.
Biography/Profile
Alvah Allen Torrance was born 1903 August 21 near Wallis, Texas to Robert Blake Torrance and Daisy Allen Torrance. He served in the United States Army during World War II, was an accomplished amateur photographer, and a Mason (Shriner).
Torrance worked for the Amicable Life Insurance Company located in Waco, Texas. He held positions as cashier, assistant secretary, and was named Vice President in 1958. As Vice President, he saw the company through its merger with American Life insurance Company based in Alabama. Torrance served on the board of several organizations including Amicable Life, the McLennan County Children’s Foundation, and the North Waco Water Supply District.
Alvah Torrance died August 22, 1990, in Waco, Texas, and is buried in Waco Memorial Park.
Scope and Content
As an officer and employee of the Amicable Life Insurance Company, Alvah Torrance was involved in many aspects of the company. The Business series includes documents chronicling the merger of the Amicable Life Insurance Company and the American Life insurance Company as well as correspondence and stockholders’ reports. In addition, there are publication copies of Insurance Record, Insurance Graphic, and the employee publication of the merged American-Amicable Life Insurance Company, Life Line. Torrance traveled to an annual conference at Beloit College in Wisconsin for several years, and travel notebooks document gas, hotel, and food prices for the period 1953-1960. Torrance also includes descriptions of weather, personal health, miles driven, and activities he participated in after the conference. Some activities include tours and stops to take scenic photographs as he drove back to Waco, Texas. One notebook even documents a trip to the Bahamas.
The Personal series documents activities and hobbies of Alvah Torrance. There are event programs from a Lee Lockwood (Masonic) Banquet in 1942, an issue of the Karem Karavan from 1944, and a 1945 history of Central Christian Church in Waco. Personal correspondence represents family interactions, community engagement, and his interest in photography. Torrance was featured on the covers of at least three publications; one for the Featherlite Corporation (Masonic Grand Lodge Memorial Temple in Waco, Texas), one for the Insurance News Graphic (traveling salesman), and one for a Baylor University Founder’s Day program (Pat Neff Hall). All three covers are included. Other photos include that of a plane crash submitted to Time Magazine, a Masonic event, and several of a woman posing at a lake.
The Slides series includes hundreds of slides documenting Torrance’s driving trips and excursions as well as the city of Waco. Slides are arranged with mostly generic folder titles but seem to be consistent with the travel notebooks in the Personal series. Slides consist of primarily architectural and landscape content but also include automobiles and some people. Places include Waco, South Dakota, Illinois, Washington, DC, Utah, and others.
Arrangement
The collection had no previous arrangement. It is now arranged in three series, Series I: Business, Series II: Personal, and Series III: Slides.
Access Restrictions
All requests for copying of materials must be submitted to The Texas Collection in writing. Please use the Request Form for Copying Materials sheet. Unpublished materials authored or otherwise produced by the creator (s) of this collection are in the public domain. There are no restrictions on use. Copyright status for other collection materials is unknown. Transmission or reproduction of materials protected by U.S. Copyright Law (Title 17, U.S.C.) beyond that allowed by fair use requires the written permission of the copyright owners. Works not in the public domain cannot be commercially exploited without permission of the copyright owners. Responsibility for any use rests exclusively with the user.
Acquisition Information
Accession No. 3085. Acquired 0-00-00
Related Resources
Related references
Find a Grave, Inc. “Alvah Allen Torrance.” Memorial #91980497. Databases. Accessed 2020 September 18.
Vaughn, Betty J. “Genealogy Report: Descendants of John Johnston, Sr.” Accessed 2020 September 18.
Index Terms
Subjects (Persons)
Torrance, Alvah A.
Subjects (Organizations)
American-Amicable Life Insurance Company (Waco, Tex.); Amicable Life Insurance Company (Waco, Tex.)
Subjects
Insurance companies -- Mergers.; Travel.
Genres
Correspondence.; Periodicals.; Photographs.; Records (Documents); Slides (Photography)
- Business, 1944-1967, undated; 1
  Administrative Information
  Physical Description
  General condition: Good.
  Biography/Profile
  The Business series, dated 1944-1967, is made up of documents related to the Amicable Life Insurance Company and documents the merger with American Life Insurance Company. Items such as by-laws, company publications, memos, stockholder reports, and travel documents are present. The series is in chronological order, and in good condition.
  Arrangement
  - Amicable Life Insurance Company, General, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Travel Expenses, 1944-1945 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Publications: Employee, 1945-1967 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Publications: General, 1946-1949 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 1949-1966 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Travel Notebooks, 1953-1960 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - American Amicable Life Insurance Company By-Laws, 1955-1967 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - American Amicable Life Insurance Company Memos, 1958-1967 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Amicable Life Insurance Company Proxy Fight, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Stockholders Report, 1962-1965 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Central Texas Iron Works Financial Statements, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - American & Amicable Life Insurance Companies Merger, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Insurance Materials, General, 1965-1966 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Texas Highway Map, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Personal, 1938-1972; 2
  The Personal series, dated 1938-1972, includes photographs, correspondence, programs, publications, and legal documents. The series is in chronological order and in good condition.
  Index Terms
  Genres
  Photographic print
  - Photographs: Events, 1938-1941 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Land Deed and Purchase Papers, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Photographs and Publications, 1940-1941 (Box 2 OVZ, Folder 1)
  - World War II Discharge Memo, Waco Army Flying School, 1942 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Programs and Publications, 1942-1951 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Correspondence, 1942-1972 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Photographs: General, circa 1943 (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Slides, undated; 3
  General condition: Excellent.
  The Slides series is listed as undated, but most likely covers the period 1953 to around 1970. The series is organized with Waco related items first, followed by scenic views. The series is in excellent condition.
  35 mm slide
  - General, undated (Box 1 OVZ, Folder 1)
  - Waco Homes (1 of 2), undated (Box 1 OVZ, Folder 2)
  - Waco Homes (2 of 2), undated (Box 1 OVZ, Folder 3)
  - Waco Memorial Park, undated (Box 1 OVZ, Folder 4)
  - Lake Waco, undated (Box 1 OVZ, Folder 5)
  - Waco, General (1 of 2), undated (Box 1 OVZ, Folder 6)
  - Waco, General (2 of 2), undated (Box 1 OVZ, Folder 7)
  - Autos (1 of 2), undated (Box 1 OVZ, Folder 8)
  - Autos (2 of 2), undated (Box 1 OVZ, Folder 9)
  - Washington, DC, undated (Box 1 OVZ, Folder 10)
  - Utah National Parks, undated (Box 1 OVZ, Folder 11)
  - Scenic Views (1 of 15), undated (Box 1 OVZ, Folder 12)
  - Scenic Views (2 of 15), undated (Box 1 OVZ, Folder 13)
  - Scenic Views (3 of 15), undated (Box 1 OVZ, Folder 14)
  - Scenic Views (4 of 15), undated (Box 1 OVZ, Folder 15)
  - Scenic Views (5 of 15), undated (Box 1 OVZ, Folder 16)
  - Scenic Views (6 of 15), undated (Box 1 OVZ, Folder 17)
  - Scenic Views (7 of 15), undated (Box 1 OVZ, Folder 18)
  - Scenic Views (8 of 15), undated (Box 1 OVZ, Folder 19)
  - Scenic Views (9 of 15), undated (Box 1 OVZ, Folder 20)
  - Scenic Views (10 of 15), undated (Box 1 OVZ, Folder 21)
  - Scenic Views (11 of 15), undated (Box 1 OVZ, Folder 22)
  - Scenic Views (12 of 15), undated (Box 1 OVZ, Folder 23)
  - Scenic Views (13 of 15), undated (Box 1 OVZ, Folder 24)
  - Scenic Views (14 of 15), undated (Box 1 OVZ, Folder 25)
  - Scenic Views (15 of 15), undated (Box 1 OVZ, Folder 26)